Let's talk about composition. So here in this example I'm showing some basic
compositions
and actually there's no wrong or right. These are just guides that can help you.
So most of the time
I'm trying to avoid the middle. So the middle on vertical or horizontal or both
or diagonal.
And some movie makers do use this on purpose for the whole movie. It's their
style of filming.
But normally you would see these kinds of compositions because this makes
more...
Yeah, it's more out of balance and feels more organic. So this feels more
natural and this
feels a bit more... Yeah.
made or artificial. So when I'm drawing, I try to stick to these kind of
compositions.
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
So when I start with a drawing or a storyboard and I want to make a story about
a house,
I decide on which point I want to start making that. So most of the time, that's
why I make
this nine sliced apart. So I decide I'm going to draw the house here.
And here's the horizon line. And maybe here's a character. So now it's, we have
here this
character and here this house. And we're avoiding the middle. And our eye gets
um, yeah, attracted to one of these points, but as well in special cases, you
can use this.
Try to watch movies and try to see if you can find these compositions.
So in this example, I'm basically doing the same, but then with all these
abstract shapes.
So here, let me draw this frame here. And for example, here we have the most
simplest with
the ball. So here we have a big ball and here's small one. So this creates
contrast.
And you can also use that for, uh, for example, here making all these shapes
think of a city or something. So here, and here's the horizon line a bit under
the middle.
Okay.
But this creates this out of balance look. And maybe if you watch it modern art,
that's basically this. So you, but they are doing a modern arts.
That is basically all about composition, creating contrast and interesting
things to, to watch.
So here, so here we have the shapes going this way. And on the other side,
we make a small one that makes this, and you can actually use this to create
your,
your own art. For example, here, if we have this drawing, then you can draw,
start drawing
on top of it to make an interesting tree out. And here's some small, some small
trees,
for example, and then you can hear even draw a character.
So,
Yeah, that is how you can think of finding interesting compositions.
What you could do is take your sketchbook and try to make your own crazy
compositions
with these things.
So here I'm saying distribution of masses.
So here these things are masses.
So here's a lot of mass and here not.
Balance of shape.
So here we have one big shape and here we have three smaller shapes.
Rhythm.
So here you're trying to get this flow into it.
So the best way to practice this is just by doing it.
Maybe make variations of what I'm showing here.
Try to see what happens if you play around with all those different shapes.
Here I'm showing rhythms.
So this could be useful if you want to make and get attention to something.
So for example, here we have this rhythm here and it's almost symmetrical.
So it's all out of balance and it creates tension and interesting.
And it feels like there's something moving.
For example, if we would draw a shot here.
And here we have these shapes going to this point.
And then we have this character here.
And then this character feels like he's being attacked or something.
And you could, for example, I'm going to do this with this shape here.
And then here, we could actually do this by maybe this is a river.
And this is a bridge, and maybe here's a tree.
And we can fix this with the correct perspective.
But this creates this interesting lines.
So try to think about rhythm in your drawing.
And this is also a great tool about guiding our eyes,
because we're following with our eyes these shapes.
So the golden ratio.
So this is actually the mathematical formula of the golden ratio.
And I don't literally use this formula, but I find it really interesting to use.
So what it means is basically this one, this six,
one, eight. And that means that this height is six, one, eight pixels. And this
side is
thousand pixels. Then if we divide here, this thousands and we get off this 618,
then we
are left with this place and then you get this shot. So that's, and that's where
the
the rule. So here, that's where the rule of thirds come from. So it's almost
this.
It's a little bit different here. You can see, but this is the, maybe the lazy
way of
the golden ratio. And you can totally do this by hand. I don't use these exact
formulas.
And you could guess it.
So then we have this here and then you can divide this shape again.
And then you can divide this shape.
Then you can divide this shape.
Then you can divide this here and this here and this here.
So what we now can do is we can take this line and draw this line
through it, something like this here.
And that's the golden ratio.
And you see this and the cool thing is the shape.
You see this shape in nature, uh, the snail house.
And for some reason, our, we find it's a pleasant thing to look at and it
helps guiding our eyes to, um, so here I'm using it loosely.
You can put this character on this line and then this gun here and here, this
thing, and then you get this, our eye.
can go through it. You can even, how to make this even better is maybe use that
there's a hill there
and so something like this. So we're getting more into the flow of line and
don't try to
use it too rigid, but try to use it loosely like showing here. Here we have this
tree
that's touching this edge and then it ends here and here is the most detail.
So it's just a guide to help you, but actually if you're watching a lot of
movies you can see it's
they use the rule of thirds and the rule of thirds is that you're defined this
in nine.
So that's basically a simplified version of the Gonerule and you'll also see
this
being used in movies as well.
Maybe a lot of times it's unintentionally or unconscious, but it's behind a lot
of art.
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
Clouds, so I was earlier talking about the written and about guiding the eye
with shapes
and with clouds you can perfectly use this to guide the eye or to frame your
character.
So what it means to frame your character is that you're using this cloud around
your character
and that makes your character stands out. So here this is also this diagonal
direction that
also helps makes yeah this tension that's more interesting that they're all
horizontal.
Here I'm using the clouds to frame the character but I'm also using the clouds
to point
at the character.
And here I saw always trying to get this nice flow
in your cloud shapes here as well,
going around the mountain.
So clouds are great to guide the eye
and to create interesting composition.
Think of that abstract shapes with the rhythm shown.
So for shortening,
I try to use foreshortening to create depth.
For example, if we're drawing an environment,
what you want to avoid is that you don't have any depth
in it.
For example, here we have this tree, branch
and then there's this.
This flower here on the ground.
Now, I think it's more interesting if we make it more, um, maybe there's this
road and then here it is.
Your roads starts really broad and gets too narrow.
So then we get this depth and also this tree branch.
It goes into the depth and here this flower is also more like this.
So then you have more of, uh, this feeling then instead of this and this, so
you're
using this, um, and try to think of it that if you have 3d.
So here this drawing has this, these angles, but this drawing has also the z, x,
um, z, s,
or x, I think it was x, so, and I think, I don't know out of my head,
I think this is I, and this is x, but I could be wrong, but don't forget the z,
x.
So try to create depth with these for shortening things. And the most easy way
to, to draw for
shortening is to use these kind of, uh, the, these kind of cylinders to first
draw it.
And then later you, you erase them and then you can draw the, the shapes inside
it.
So try to think of it, also with this flower that you're,
so here we're looking a bit on the side of these petals
and here more onwards then.
So we're getting more of this depth.
So you can also think of it as sheet of paper.
So here it is from the front, this from the sides,
but it's more interesting if we're showing
this sheet of paper like this,
that we're seeing a bit of the back,
a bit of the front, that creates depth.
And this can be a stylistic choice.
I'm not saying that this is always wrong,
but I like to draw more in this style.
It's a little bit more realistically.
So.
For example, with the clouds, I'm using a big shape versus a small shape,
and then an even bigger shape. And then again, so I'm trying to play around with
getting this nice play with big shape, small shape, medium, et cetera, to create
contrast in your shapes. For example, also, this is more like graphic or an
icon.
You see this in 2D TV shows. Within animation, feature animation, you often see
this more.
Unless it's really stylistic. Stylistic shows go more to this. But really, if
you're storyboarding,
it doesn't even matter that much because it's all about the story. But
I do use these kind of shapes more, even when I'm
I'm storyboarding. So basically using a big shape versus a medium shape for
small shape and favorably using middle, big shape, small shape. So it's so watch
out that you're not, if you're drawing a snowman for example, this is dull that
all these shapes are even size. But you want to use contrast of small shape,
bigger, biggest. But maybe this is even more interesting. Middle, small, big. So
you
are having more random, especially when you're working with nature or organic
shapes. You can also use this in your your effect. So when you're drawing
effects, if you draw an explosion, don't draw the explosion symmetrical like
this.
Let's try to draw it more here, playing around with those.
I think this is even too symmetrical.
So it's really natural for our humans to draw things really symmetrical.
Yeah, maybe this needs to be a big shape.
It can be really hard sometimes to do this correctly.
So maybe making this here, this here.
So try to play around here.
For example, here is this.
Here, this is all parallel, these lines.
And here I'm playing a bit around with getting more or in even shapes.
Also with water. So try to think about how you can make these organic shapes and
it's all about using
so you can show that here so this is parallel but you can also use this
or you can do this but you can also do this
or you can do a straight one against this or if it's a really busy line
you could do complex versus simple and so on
a rule of thirds so basically this is a little bit like this golden ratio but
then really simplified
and you can also use this then when you have this
draw these lines to it and then you can draw things along these lines. So let me
show that with this example I'm giving here. So here first draw this shape and
then you divide it through nine parts, taking different color. So let's draw the
horizon line here so it can be a bit above or a bit under this line and you
can also put it here but don't put it here. So here and then we're drawing three
here against this line here and here here. So if we're using this line that's
going
through these parts.
How we can use that in this composition is for example here
drawing this tree against this line and here we have this bush here
and then here in the distance we have this shape here
and then here within the mountain.
So you're really trying to use this really loosely.
We can even and I personally never use that but some people do is making these
lines
adding these lines also and then you can use this for drawing these shapes for
example here and there.
So again these are just guides that you can use.
And another one that I find really interesting and you don't hear a lot about it
is your path.
So here if we have this shot
and we're making a square in it for example here like this and then here
and then also on the other side and I think it's not used
this more a lot because with these white screens it works less better than with
our old TVs
that weren't this broad it's more like this.
But now our phones and stuff and our screens are so broad that this
works less better because you want to have this that this green box is here
and it's purplish here and you don't want them to have like this.
because then you would also have this middle and that almost happens when you're
using
cinema screens with this technique. But the interesting thing about this area is
that you
then yeah here you can use this these points also for interesting and for
example here
then you can decide to put the wall line here and so for example the ceiling is
then here and the
floor is here and then you can even draw this character here standing and maybe
there's a door
here. So again not too symmetrical so that's maybe we can choose to make this
character.
Even bigger so that we're seeing it in the front here
So so you can use these as guides to to create all these
All these compositions
I find this one really interesting. I don't use it that much because it's
I have the feeling it works more with all those old tv screens than with the new
ones
So I like to use this one because it's fast and easy
Or actually this one I use the most
So a good way to practice this is by watching movies
And make studies so when you're uh watching a movie
Pause the the movie
And for example, then we're seeing these two characters
Looking down, and this one is looking here.
So try to think about what kind of composition
does here and does fits with this one.
So if I'm defining it through nine,
then you can see, yeah, now I did a bit wrong,
but you can see that this character's on this line
and this other character is on this line.
This character is a little bit higher
and this one is a bit lower.
So what they try to do is
putting a head here and a head here.
And what I said, you don't have to put it
exactly on these points
because then not every shot would look the same.
But it's a guide.
Here it is also interesting.
So I was talking about to avoid these things,
but here you can see how a movie director is using this.
to create this symmetrical feeling. And I think it's because there's this
kind of, maybe there's this harmony, almost like the yin-yang sign.
Also here, sometimes it can help to create these triangles. So we're seeing this
character is looking at this character and this character is looking, actually
is looking here.
Does it force our eyes to this point? And this moves again up. So you need to
take a little bit freedom in it. And yeah, again, it's just these signs,
but you can actually see the shapes in when you're watching movies. For example,
this shot, there's this total out of balance. Here's
everything that's happening here, but not here. So there's this balance. And you
can see that
this movie maker will probably use that in other shots as well.
It's their signature in the movie. So again, here it is a golden ratio.
And maybe you can also find other compositions. But it's really interesting to
look at how they
used balance to create these kinds of shots. These are also some interesting
things you can
use to get the attention. So here, I sometimes use that. So when you're
boarding, so for example,
we're drawing this frame here. And we're having this character here.
And then let's take this bit of a gray color.
Here we have all these shapes in the foreground.
But we're using this camera
where the foreground should be out of focus. How we could do this?
Filter, Blur, and then go to Gaussian Blur. Yeah. And we can make this out of
focus.
However, how much you want. And then you get this really attention on this
character.
It's also interesting to use, to play around a bit with this viewer. So that
you're maybe in
the shot, you first see these two bunnies.
sitting here, and then we're seeing this character coming out of the, behind the
horizon.
And then because you have this size difference, it creates this interesting, and
you can play
around with, with those things to make interesting shots. Depth. So, atmospheric
perspective,
is this called? So things in the distance are looking more fogged out because of
the
stuff that is in the air. So things that are more in the distance are more
grayed out. So
this is really black, and this is more grayed out. Framing. So again, I think
I've said this before,
but you can use objects to create this frame around the character to make it
really stand out.
Uh, open space. So this feels really like empty. So this is interesting,
establishing shots.
You're seeing, oh, he's alone. He's, he's walking. Maybe he has a goal. Maybe
he's not.
It feels like he's walking with these. He, yeah, maybe he's trying to survive or
something.
Yeah. Water to show the reflection. So this is effect shots to make it extra
special.
So the rule of thirds, so you can actually start, maybe you have a script and
then you,
you start with drawing the, the shots with these, if I didn't know, and then you
have,
and you know that these are the focus points and that you want to tell a story
with that.
So maybe you are telling a story about two characters talking to each other.
which character is important and which which character is feeling weaker.
So here we maybe have this strong or maybe here it is this teacher
that is bigger or something and here we have this kid listening.
So then you you create this contrast between these characters and then I'm using
these
these points. But you can start with using these abstract points to to imagine
what you want to tell and how you want to use the composition to tell.
So here I'm showing some things and you can use perspective.
So this is a vanishing point and here we have these perspective points
aiming at this point. So this point gets really the attention.
So here for example here you can use this here.
So because if we would draw maybe there's a big sign sign here.
So these lines are pointing to this character.
Maybe there's a road here, so this road is aiming at this character.
Eyes on one third, I'm using that a lot, what I just shown in the previous
image.
Uh, or here creating this internship.
So here you can see the most basic, uh, compositions, but for storyboarding
where you need to draw really fast, this is really, uh, useful.
So drawing backgrounds, um, yeah, basically the same starting with this,
this shot.
So that's many, let me take a sketch brush.
So if this one, um,
putting the horizon line on one here and then drawing the house here,
often starting with this basic shapes.
And then, uh, here using this rhythm, trying to find this rhythm with the
shapes.
So here, sometimes I draw some abstract shapes and then I try to come up with
things to, uh,
to draw, for example, here, this fence, here, these bushes here, this tree.
So starting with these abstract shapes, and then I'm starting to draw all these
construction,
with all these, um, 3d shapes actually. Um, so here it's abstract and here I'm
trying to add
more depth and that it makes more sense. Then I clean it up.
And a lot of times I'm just using two or three types of shadows.
Not more of that, because you're storyboarding and you're not making final
drawings,
then it would take way too long time to actually draw.
Composition characters, I think I've also covered this already,
with having two characters against each other.
Because this character is a bit lower than this character, so
this self-esteem seems lower.
So this character feels more dominant and this character feels weaker.
Again, try to use as few shadows as you can.
So sometimes when I really need to draw something fast for storyboarding,
and you have two characters.
And you want to add some backgrounds.
Sometimes you can just add this
if you want to be really fast
to give the impression that there's a roof or a sky.
But sometimes this is a way more than enough,
just this perspective.
Positive and negative space.
So this really is important for the readability.
So this is all has to do with silhouette.
So for example, if we're drawing a running character
and we're drawing the character like this,
you can see what's really happening.
But if we draw the character with the clear silhouettes,
he's putting his arms more out and like this,
it's easier to read.
So this maybe...
seems obvious but yeah a lot of times this is not happening correctly and it's
also in
the background so try to find an interesting balance with black and white and
you also
here I find yeah this is super interesting right this yin yang sign
so here that you have a balance or out of balance but yeah you can create a lot
of clarity with
using these two so think about the silhouettes and that things are readable so
which you can
even sometimes use so I'm showing that here the power of three can can use a lot
but
if you want to make more complex drawing you don't have to use more than three
colors for example if we have
Let me show here again, can use this one again.
So now there's, it's either black or white, but if we're using a gray tone, for
example
here, that adds a lot.
So then you also get this point of interest here.
So I try to use for storyboarding, uh, to, uh, values that sometimes you can
use, uh,
use three to, to give more, um, yeah, for example, especially for something like
this.
And again, with storyboarding, you're using more line work.
Um, but it is interesting and try to avoid using too much values in your, in
your drawings.
Uh, contrast, um.
Of course, for storyboarding, you're avoiding colors, but sometimes you do use
some, some
colors, but let's start with value.
So when we're making a background or a thing, and then you have, and you want to
have this
character stand out.
And if you make the rest really black and white and this character black, then
it stands
out, but you can also use it.
And then here, why it's so that's creates, yeah, really our attention is really
built.
So the biggest contrast is by using a value.
So if you really want to let something stand out, value is really great.
Proximity, uh, means that you, uh, have all these shapes close to each other.
And then we have this character standing alone.
So that makes this character really getting the attention.
So Yui, so for example, if everything is green and use one red thing, that thing
stands out as well.
So we're going from, this is the strongest contrast, then proximity, then Yui.
Edge, yeah, and these blurred out things don't get the attention, but this sharp
thing
gets our attention. Direction, so yeah, where our eyes are trained or evolved to
pick out those
things that stand out also with that direction. Or the saturation, for example,
this all green,
when we're looking at color, for example, this is our saturation, so this is
100%,
this is 50% and this is zero, white. But if we have all
thing with this and then we put in one thing this here. I hope you can see it
here. Maybe
I can make this a little bit lighter so this value will stand out. But this is
something
you would use more with painting. You rarely use it with storyboarding.
Maybe UI sometimes, maybe you want to use really occasional for some kind of
effect.
You want to use some UI shapes, everything is square and you put one round shape
and your
eye will get caught by that round shape. Proportion, all small shapes, one big
shape.
Texture, that everything is really smooth. But one thing that has a lot of
detail or texture
gets the attention. So don't put details everywhere. Try to put details on one
point.
reading direction, and that's really important
for storyboarding, and this is in some cultures
really different, so in the West,
we're reading from the top left to the right
and then towards the bottom, so we're also using that
when we're seeing, for example, if we're seeing a car
going from left to right, we have the feeling
that car is going somewhere, but if it's going
from right to left, we have the feeling
he's going back home, the same with character,
so this character is going to work,
but then we're seeing he's going back,
maybe he forgot his keys or something,
so try to think about why you're seeing
you're using left to right or which way your character or car is moving to.
Here again the bird is flying away maybe looking for food and he's coming back
with food from the right to left bottom. So actually here this is this movement
and then here this
movement. Same yeah this is with the corner so if we're having this car you want
to have this
space in front of the car maybe you're using the screen to move along with the
car so it's
always staying here or the car moves out of the screen but what you don't want
is when you're
starting the scene starts to arise with this because then you...
Yeah, it feels just weird, especially here with this character.
So when you don't want to, maybe it's a bit confusing because there you see this
here.
So when we're having a character that is looking at the sea, you don't want to
draw it like
this.
You want to move the character here and let him having this eye of this space to
look
at.
For example, here this spaceship, don't put the spaceship too much to this
space.
Let it have the space here and not here behind it, but in front of.
Tangents, so that's something you want to avoid when you're drawing.
Basically, it's when two objects or lines touch each other at the same borders.
You can also see like this, if you're having these lines going like this here,
it gets
so much attention and unless it's on purpose, but most of the time you don't
want that.
So how you better can draw these lines is that maybe like this, or these shapes
use overlap
like this.
That creates also more depth.
You can see it with this, for example, if you have this car with this tree, it
feels
like this car is against the tree, so you can choose to move it a bit so there's
more
space between it, or use this overlap.
to really show that the car is behind the tree.
so shadow and light again I'm trying to use as few values as I can so when I for
example we have a ball and we want to shade it first I decide where's the
light coming from from this corner and then fill this so a good exercise to do
this is to take a light and maybe a ball or an object and see what how you can
shade the ball with one one tone and maybe you can use these for when you're
drawing in the head use these kinds of shadows for for that and again
This shows that you can do a lot with only showing one
With only showing one shade of value you can do a lot