Perspective is really important for storyboarding. So let me show that. So here
I've made three
versions of shots with different perspectives. So here, let me draw this box.
So this is the frame. So how to draw perspective? I made a whole ebook about
this and it's a pretty
big subject. But let me go really quickly over it. Sorry. So here we have this
box and let's
draw this horizon line. So you first pick the horizon line you want to use. So
this is a low,
this is on one thirds. So
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
then you choose a vanishing point and this vanishing point can be anywhere on
this line
and then you're drawing these lines from also from the other side.
You can also choose to go for one point perspective and then we have the basic
perspective
and you can use this for example to draw a wall.
So here we're following this line and then we're going straight up
and then or let's make this line here and then we can also follow this line here
for this.
So that is how I use perspective. We can also add a ceiling like this
so here so now we have this this wall
and then you can draw this now you can draw characters here so and actually
because this is lower let me draw this so here so what we're actually seeing
here would look something like this so two people in a room and the ceiling is
somewhere something like here and the camera is at this height so here it's
the eye level and again that's a whole different subject and I'm telling more
about that in perspective ebook but I wanted to share how I draw a basic
perspective like this so let me also show
those other ones like you can also choose to draw the horizon line a bit higher
like
here.
So you just draw a horizon line and then there's a person or let me draw these
perspective
lines again.
You can also guess them so when you're storyboarding you want to draw quickly so
maybe you don't
draw the whole finishing point etc but you make these rough lines and that's
totally
fine.
So here, draw this character here and this other character here.
like this and how this would look like so we could draw again this here this
wall here is ceiling something like this so how would this look with the camera
so then the camera will be here and now the camera is at the eye level so here
drawn a character here and a character here so this character is this character
this character is this character and then there's the wall this like this
high so that is two-thirds horizon line and you can also use it to draw these
more organic perspectives
So when you're drawing something from a bird's view, so when the camera is
really high,
the horizon line is somewhere here. So imagine that this point is here and then
drawing all
these lines like this here. And for storyboarding, most of the time I'm drawing
them freehand
because of the time. And then you can draw in the, for example, here, this is a
city.
So there's a building here, here, here. So there's also a three-point
perspective,
but for storyboarding, I'm almost never using it. Or it's really important for
the
effect, but most of the time I'm avoiding that.
so here so how would this look from the side we have the camera that is aiming
down then here we have this character on this building and it's looking at all
these other buildings so you have this kind of shot so let's take a look at
crouch let's go down a bit and let's see this so we're calling this a one shot a
two shots the three shots four shots and it's and you can continue making five
shots and six shots etc so the two refers to two characters
and but you can also go to a group shot so group shot or a crowd shot and yeah
it's it's used for to really clarify that there are four characters in it yeah
if
if you want you can even put numbers besides them to make more clearer so maybe
you have
multiple shots from different views and then having those numbers that it can
help
show which character what is but you don't see this often but you could use it
so what i'm trying to show here with these red lines is to group the the people
so especially
here with those big groups for example if we're
drawing a shot and there's a building here.
And there are people waiting.
So it's really good to first maybe draw a big shape
and then draw all these people in this shape.
so like this then you have this flow in it instead of just drawing all these
people here we have this building all these people separate
So that's going to look messy.
So try to group the people.
So effects for storyboarding, and you want to keep it simple, but for example,
you could
use if you want to make something cold, you can use this blue or for example,
these trees
in the distance that is called atmospheric perspective.
So when something is in the distance, things tend to fade out.
Try to look out of the window and try to see, compare the farthest away thing
you can see
compared to a closer thing.
Like if you see a tree close to where you're looking from, you can see all the
colors and
all the values.
If you look at the tree that is really, really far away.
It will look with less contrast in a value.
So that's what I tried to mimic with these colors, with these fade out values.
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
So you can also use the snow particles like I did here.
So here it's snowing quite softly.
Here I used this blur effect of this soft brush.
And then you have that mist effect.
One simple way to do that in Photoshop is to use the gradient tool.
So that is under this paint bucket tool, we have this gradient tool.
And then you can drag it and put it here.
And then you can have that mist effect.
And keep it all simple and really functional.
All those things.
So heavy storm.
Um, so we're choosing a direction and we're making those snow, uh, flakes
longer, so like this, and then because of it's this direction, it feels
like there's this energy behind.
And then we have this character that is going in the opposite direction.
So when you're walking through a storm, you're leaning forward.
So you won't get blown away.
Um, here, soft brush effect to create this mist effect.
So here, and we're taking this soft brush.
So what I'm doing in Photoshop, you have shape dynamics, but you also have
transfer a bit, uh, uh, the hardness on zero.
Okay.
so and you can draw in those soft mist effects
So let me see here.
Yeah, and this is then extreme and combined.
So you can see that I used,
let me take the,
oh, let me select the right brush.
So I want to have this hard brush with the shape dynamics.
Here you can see I used these lines for the character
also to add some effects
and also using these wind strokes.
So those are a couple of effects you could use.
Here are some more,
often using foreground and background elements.
Also here again,
here in this foreground it's quite dark
and in the background it's lighter.
So that's again that atmospheric perspective and that will help you
create depth in your drawings.
You can also use blur.
So now the focus is on this character using foreshortening.
So that's this perspective trick that when you're drawing an arm or cylinder
this side looks bigger than this side when this is farther away.
So if we're looking at the camera.
So this is what the side looks like.
But here this is closer to the camera.
So that is this part and this is farther away and it looks that part.
Again that's perspective.
How I draw, let me draw this shot to show that a bit.
So here we're drawing these shots.
And we want to have this bunny here.
And let's draw this perspective.
Freehand, something like this.
And then we have this bunny, the head, the body, the legs.
So then you can draw on top of this circle.
So here using this cylinder to draw the arm.
And then here and et cetera.
So I'm using these balls to draw the character and this perspective.
When to cut in your shots, this can be quite hard and complex, but try to keep
it as simple
as possible.
So here we see an over the shoulder shot, character two is speaking to character
one,
then character one starts to talk.
So you actually see him starting to talk, then you cut while character one is
talking,
you cut to this shot.
So there's this continuation in it.
And then this character listening.
So the same now if this character is going to talk again, so we would have a
shot where
he opens his mouth.
So this is the best drawing ever.
So and then here we have this character starting to listen.
And then we cut again to a next shot
where we see this character from the front.
And then this one is listening.
The same when, so this person is reaching out
for his pencil.
At the moment that he moves his arm,
let the viewer show that he's moving his arm a bit.
Then you cut to the shot where you see the hand
continuation with that movement.
And then he grabs the hand.
So if you leave this out, it can be a bit too hard.
The cuts can be too hard.
So you have that continuation of movement
in your, before your cuts.
Here's another one.
So we see this character ready to go eat, but then here's a sound and you see
his head moving.
And here at this point, you see also a little bit movement. And then he looks at
the dog and
he knows where the sound's coming from. But then there's this continuation in
the,
in what's happening and moving. So some storyboard rules.
So these kinds of storyboards you will see in, often when they're working,
those are used for television shows often, these kinds of storyboards.
And they have the panel, et cetera, background scene. And here this,
here also this part. And for oftentimes for movies, it's different. For movies,
they
often just only use this part.
So let me explain a bit what everything is.
So here we have the scene.
And so this is for example, scene one
and the movie starts with scene one.
And you have the panel A.
So scene three, panel A, scene three, panel B, et cetera.
And you're using these background numbers
to tell, or you can use,
here you can use the backgrounds
from B also used in scene three, panel A.
Here you can put notes for telling about
what kind of effects there are.
A dialogue, so what they are talking about.
Transition, what kind of transition is between the cuts
and between the shots.
Slugging is for the timing.
So how long.
The shot should be in, uh, in, uh, in the screen.
So here we have this girl walking in and here, uh, using this arrow, uh, you
can,
you, you can draw this arrow on top of it, uh, here safe area.
Um, that is for, especially when you're working for TV, you're working with
different, uh, televisions at home.
So this area at some, uh, televisions, you will see this, but others you won't.
So this is the safe area here.
You want to have all the, the action.
Um, so here, um, three a, so this is still the same scene, but the new cuts.
So then you're just placing an A behind it and then you.
It starts counting again with the panel A.
So this scene 3A, panel A, and there's a new background.
And you can see the dialogue here.
You can use here for, if you're using a pen,
you draw those red arrows like this on top of it.
So that means that there's pen
and you can draw between those shots.
So sometimes they even post post-its
on these kind of sheets to do what they want.
Here you can see this transition.
So here's this cross dissolve,
just putting a cross between it
and we're calling it cross dissolve.
That means that this shot fades into this shot.
Here's this zoom in.
So with those red lines, et cetera.
So again, this is how they are using.
Or at least a lot of studios are working with these kind of sheets in for
television animation.
So here are some explanation. So this is called a fade out. So that means when
a shot, so we have this shot here, transfers into another shot. And you also
have this
cross to solve. But the difference between, let me see how I can best tell this.
Let me
just draw this here. So here we have this character like this here, and then
it's fade
out into into black. So like this, or you can have it starts with.
And black shots, oh, and then it fades in this here.
And you also have that cross to solve I showed earlier,
and then it's looking like this.
Like this, or yeah, you're trying to avoid
to make those shots too different.
So maybe something like this.
So that's the cross dissolve.
You also have a wipe dissolve.
What that means is that, yeah, let me draw that here.
And maybe there's an elephant like this.
Then we have this frame here.
And that moves in like this.
So you have this shot here
and then this other shot moves in.
But you will see, and I never really use this a lot.
But it's used in, you don't see it a lot in movies,
but then it's actually, you would have this line
or this completely different shot between there.
So that's when basically a different shot is moving in.
Star Wars is often using that.
A ripple dissolve, so that's kind of when the other shots
turns into the next shot, then you have that ripple effect. So think of it as if
you see that
water effect, so that for example, again I need to have this on a brush,
pen pressure, let me take this sketch brush,
here in the first shot you see this, this character,
and then it fades, it ripples out like this,
then the next shot looks really like this, can't almost see anything about it,
and then
it starts moving into these two characters
until you have that.
until you see those two characters like this. So it's a transition between those
two shots
like that. So the iris out or in is basically, yeah, think of the Looney Tunes
stuff when you
have that circle that is moving in and then it's until it's completely black.
And that's when you often you see that at the end of a movie or TV show.
So some more cuts and effects.
So sometimes you can use this,
so then you have maybe a shot
and then it moves to the shots of someone's house.
And then you can use this swoosh pen,
for example, when you're,
oh, I need to go to home to warm,
to warn my girlfriend.
And then you're moving the swoosh pen,
then you see the home.
Edge swipe, again, that's what you see a lot with,
for example, with Star Wars,
where you see this black box going to the screen.
And you can also use it with the shots or something.
So clock wipe,
and that means that it starts.
you get this effect.
So then this thing starting to get filled like this
until it's really black.
Then it's starting to fill on and on.
But you can just use this symbol.
So here is this cross to solve you're using
between those shots are fade out or fading.
So again, when you're working on a movie shots,
what I'm doing when I'm working on a storyboard
for more for a movie, I'm just drawing the whole shots.
And this, so then there's no.
I'll make one drawing like this and then the next drawing I'm also making like
this.
So there's no space to make these crosses on the sides.
That's often used for more for television.
So the mouse storyboard.
So this is one I made some time ago
and what I want to show here,
you have these kinds of different levels of drawing.
So this is most really detailed
and usually I don't work with such a detailed drawing
because this takes a lot of time to actually draw.
However, you could use this,
especially for when you're working for commercials
or something they want to have really detailed storyboards
often because they are presenting it to people
who don't have storyboard knowledge.
So they really need, it's almost a comic.
So here I already made it a little bit more simple, a bit less details, but
still a lot.
So if we go to the next one, you can see I left out a lot of details.
Sometimes I just draw the floor like these perspective lines, even here.
So and just one shade of shadow.
And I usually storyboard like this because it's fast
and easy and still clear to see what is happening.
So here I made the summary of that.
Yeah, most of the studios draw in this kind of storyboards.
And I would recommend you to go to Google and type in your favorite animation
movie
and type storyboards behind it and you will find the storyboards.
And most of the time they look like this.
And sometimes you see storyboards that are drawn like this and those are
most of the time made for commercials. And of course there's also something
between.
So, birth camera.
Here we see this.
Yeah, well, how do I want to tell this? So here, yeah. So a lot of times I'm
starting
with a floor plan. So, and that's basically drawing from the top, the whole
scene, just
really basic. And it helps me to know where, how I want to plan everything. So,
and this
was the story that there was this bird with his mouse on top of him. And this
bird is flying
under.
this bridge. And here you can see the different cameras. So this is one camera
that's moving in
this and that. So what's happening, this camera is also flying along, but then
it's also rotating,
so it's following this bird. And then when the bird is flying under the bridge,
then we cut to the second camera. So and then I start drawing it basically in.
Here's the zoom in of this character. And then we're going back with the camera,
and then the camera starting to rotate a little bit. And then the camera stands
still.
And then we see him flying under the bridge. And then we have the shot of the
birds from underneath
and I will show that in the next ones. So here you can actually see, so this is
a rough,
also rough planning. So
I won't show anyone else this, but this is the final storyboard. And so here
this camera
is moving like this. So here we're seeing it from the sides and here from the
back.
So here, let me see. Yeah, here also this plan, how it looks from the top. So
when
something complicated, you can draw these drawings from the top to plan it all
out.
So again, this is then the zooming and the camera zooms out. And when it's
zoomed out,
I choose to decide to rotate the camera to follow the bird and character. So
it's also
revealing. So because this is our hero and this is the friend, so we're making
revealing this bird.
in this shot.
So here we have this, again, the shot.
So this is when he's going under the bridge or the jump.
So here we're following these birds
and the camera is following at the same space as the birds
and here it stands still at this point.
Then you can see that the bird is flying farther away
and then we're making the cut here.
You see him flying beneath the bridge.
What's happening here, here we have this camera
and this camera stays at this position.
The bird flies to us and then over the camera
and the camera moves, yeah, it makes this rotation.
Basically this from the side, it looks like this.
So here's the bird here.
When the bird is here, the camera goes this rotation, and then here, like this.
So the camera makes this rotation.
And again, drawing these kind of little drawings helped me plan it out a bit.
So whenever a shot is really complicated, try to draw those things out first.
And then I also want to talk a bit about how to develop your own storyboards.
So as a storyboard artist, it's important to know how to write your own stories.
I really see that as a thing that I find really difficult to do, but still it's
really good to do.
You don't have to become a story writer, but making your own stories can really
help,
because it shows you know the rules and how to work with material.
So start with a simple idea for a story.
It can be just a simple Alinea, just really basic.
Then draw in the main characters.
And with storyboarding, you're not a character designer,
but it can help too.
So sometimes you're so early in the process that there's no character artist
who made the characters yet.
So you can make the first proportions.
So these ones will help you with drawing the storyboard,
because then you already thought about the design.
And also think about, yeah, for example, the bully.
So I made this big guy to, yeah.
To fill in that stereotype that, that you can see that he's a bully without
even reading the text, the friends, et cetera.
So think if the description matches the official, how they look.
So, um, With that, uh, with that small story, you can already start drawing,
uh, maybe four drawings where you're showing the main, the most important shots
of the,
of the, uh, of the story.
And we call those story beats.
You can also draw more, but, um, the ways that you drawing the most important
drawings,
and you can just draw a couple.
So you can use this also for when you're making the pitch for your story.
So then you, uh, take your summary of your, uh, and you make it.
Uh, a script and here I choose to make just a simple, it's not even one sheet of
paper.
And, uh, here you can see it's act one.
So the beginning of the story and act two, and this is then the part.
Remember for the beginning of this course where I showed, uh, so this,
I can draw the circle.
So this is one, two, three, four.
So at the beginning, and then there's the second act and then the third act.
So act one, and, um, this is, these two are act two together and act three.
Three.
And when I have, uh, made this script.
I start scribbling really rough these, uh, images before I go, uh, continue with
storyboarding.
And I do that because I like to put it on paper first before I start to really
draw everything
out. And some people don't even use these thumbnails. They go sit back and they
close
their eyes and they're going to imagine how everything looks. And then they
simply start
storyboarding. But I like to plan, uh, ahead. So first drawing all these
different shots.
So, um, this is part of the final storyboard I made for that story.
So after I script and have those thumbnails, I just simply start with the first
shot.
And, uh, yeah, start drawing in out all these scenes. So maybe you start,
so these are a bit clean up. Maybe you start super, super rough
and then you go, uh, clean it up once you like it.
Because, uh, also with this storyboard, I really changed, uh, changed a lot and
there's a lot
of work.
So what I would recommend for your portfolio, if you want to become a storyboard
artist,
it's really good to, to write your own story, um, keep it quite short, short.
So the script, I would recommend keeping it in one, uh, A4 paper, one sheet of
paper,
and then, um, use that to draw your storyboards and maybe make, uh, I think I've
made a storyboards
of 180 panels.
So don't go over 200, uh, panels because that's just too much and, um, yeah,
make whole story
in those 200 pages or make one scene in 200 pages of a movie, um, and showing
that you
can do something on that on your own.
will convince studios that you will be able to, um, that they give you the
script and that you
can use it to, to make a strong scene of that. So that was the storyboarding
course.
I hope you liked it and let me know if you have some questions about it. And
again, storyboarding
is great for if you want to become, um, there's a lot of opportunities for
storyboarding also
because it's a really hard job. There's, you need to be able to draw good and
fast.
And, uh, you need to know a lot about story. You need to have a lot of
concentration because it's
a lot of work. Um, but it's really cool because basically you're a director,
you, you, you're an
actor, you, you're a cameraman. Uh, you can draw a lot. You can work on the
biggest movies and, uh,
and so on. So it's a really good choice.
So I hope you liked it and good luck with making your own storyboard. Thanks.