Hi everyone! So in this video I'm going to talk about storyboarding.
And storyboarding is used to make animations, stories, commercials and it's even
used in games.
And it's a way to visualize your idea in quick sketches so you can use that to
create the story
and see where it works and where it doesn't. So let's start with the first
lesson.
So coming up with ideas. I think everyone can recognize this. You finally have
time to draw
and but you don't know what you can start drawing. So you start to go and think.
And a natural reaction is, at least for me, is that I go on surfing on the
internet,
looking at social media.
And I tell myself that it's for getting inspiration, but basically it's just
procrastination.
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
So just not starting on it.
Sometimes I'm even going to play some games.
But it does help. It can help you ease up your mind and make you a bit more
relaxed.
But then you realize you just need to start.
A lot of times good ideas come from when you're under the shower or when you're
doing groceries.
Or even when you're driving in the car or when you're in the train.
What does help is to really think a lot about it when you're behind your PC or
when you're writing in your sketchbook.
But when you laid it next to you...
and you go do something else, the back in your mind is still working on it.
And sometimes when I can't come up with an idea, I start really basic. Like here
this girl with
this house, or here this character with the pet, or maybe something from your
childhood.
Starting really simple can help you come up with ideas. But yeah, coming up with
ideas is hard work.
And then sometimes it clicks when you're at a place where you won't expect it.
So...
What helps me is this method I learned from the Hero's Journey.
Hero's Journey is a book I can really recommend and it's about the journey a
hero makes throughout a story.
So, I think I can also use this image here.
Let's place this one here and this one here.
So, often times a story starts from home.
So, here we see a character, a farmer working on his field.
And then he gets an invite, maybe a letter, maybe there is someone knocking on
the door.
And then there is the refusal.
So, here he gets the letter.
But he says, I don't, I want to stay at my home place.
But a lot of times there is some mentor kind of character.
Think of a wizard or maybe it's just someone else who he looks up to.
And, um, he convinces the hero to go on an adventure and this going on
adventure here in this circle, you can see here, you have this normal life.
And here's the adventure.
So here's this border, the hero needs to cross.
And sometimes you really literally see they're going through a portal or a door,
or they going to the plane to a different country.
So when they're in this new, uh, adventure in this special world, um, this, this
world is really different and they need to train.
So they need to, the idea behind the hero journey
is that the hero will make this kind of growth.
He will learn some new things.
So he will train and then he will go to the challenge,
for example, to a castle.
But then he will fail.
So this is most of the time halfway through the movie.
And that's point the hero doesn't know.
Yeah, maybe he will give up.
Maybe he will almost give up.
But then he, a lot of times there are friends
who encourage him to go on and then he gets this reward.
Then he will try.
Um, so then you will have a reward so he can go to challenge, make the challenge
again.
So for example, this in, in this case, it can be a Schwartz or something.
Um, I think it's important to, to try to watch movies and try to recognize these
things and also read that book from, um, the hero's journey about this.
So at this point, maybe the hero goes back to their normal
world and has the final battle.
Because of this reward, the hero can, can beat the final battle.
This can be a dragon, or it can be a personal fight or something.
It can be also an inverse battle.
But where, uh, the most important thing is that he gets back to the normal,
his normal world, his normal life.
but he can beat the final battle and because of that he has this growth.
And now he gets back to the point where he started in the movie
or in the story and he made some kind of growth in it.
So he's back at home and it's the same person plus growth.
So think of a lot of stories, a lot of movies are starting somewhere
and the first scene a lot of times looks a lot like the last scene.
And that's also because the hero made this kind of progression in the story.
And this way of making stories that's being used in ancient Greek.
And it's a really great way of telling a story with a message.
And also these stories are often built up out of three acts.
So we have the act one, that's the start of the story.
So that's basically...
So turn this off.
So this is basically act one.
And this is act two.
It's the middle, but most of the time it's the biggest part of the story.
And then we have act three.
And that's the last part of that circle.
So there are also these points.
So here, this point is a lot of times the inciting incident.
So that means that the hero, there's happening something to the hero
that makes him choose to go into the adventure.
And there's also the climax.
And that's often the time when the hero goes back to the...
to the normal, to normal life, but going to battle that last battle.
So that's the climax.
And you can also see that here in this graph, it goes up and then it goes down
again to the resolution and the resolution means when he's home, but then you
will
see that he's learned something.
And again, I'm not really a writer, but still, it's really good to know some
basics about this, but because this will help you understand story more.
And, uh, again, I'm not a writer.
I'm sometimes I make storyboards and then a lot of times I, this helps
me understand those stories more.
So I would really recommend, um, reading some textbooks about
writing stories from writers.
And that makes also.
For example, when you're a storyboard artist can also really help you to talk to
writers and ask them questions. So in a story, a lot of times you have all these
different
characters. Of course you have the hero, but you also have the mentor, some kind
of the dead figure
Subtitled by
online-courses.club
We compress knowledge for you!
or the person the hero is looking up to. So we have the sidekick. And a sidekick
can add some
comic relief, can help humanize the hero because sometimes the hero is really
this perfect guy,
but the sidekick can help tone it down. The herald, yeah, it doesn't have to be
a bad person,
but it can be someone who makes the hero going into the special worlds. For
example,
it can be the inciting incident.
The herald steals something from the hero and the hero makes the decisions to go
chase after him
and learn more about what's behind it. And there's also the trickster. Think
about all
the funny characters in movies and stories. We have the shapeshifter. You quite
see this
character a lot. It's a person that maybe he seems A or B, but in the end it
appears to be the opposite.
We have the guardian. So sometimes for a character to go to the special world or
go somewhere,
there's a guardian in front of it that gives a challenge to the hero. And the
guardian doesn't
need to be bad, but it's some kind of test for the hero. And of course we have
the villain, the evil, the shadow.
So this is maybe, and it doesn't have to be someone else.
It's going to also be in the hero.
So we all have our shadows.
So you can really use this figure early.
Again, I learned this from the hero journey.
And if you want to learn more about it, check that out.
I just wanted to give some basics ideas of where I learned this from
and what kind of techniques I'm using to create my own stories
or helping understand stories more.
So a big part of storyboarding is composition.
And composition helps you read what's going on in the image.
For example, here, this is really hard to, where do we need to look at first?
I don't know.
Maybe this, but maybe for you it's this, or maybe for someone else is this,
but here it's more clear.
So we, here you can see, oh, it's about two characters are meeting each other.
This character is bigger.
So maybe we are this character and we are seeing this other character.
And then, yeah, you, you get this composition.
And also this road helps also this composition.
And also this framing, these objects help framing these two characters.
And in this tutorial, I will talk more about composition and how to use it.
So aspect ratio.
So when we're going to make a storyboard, we're working on a canvas.
And for example, if we're going to make a cinema movie in a cinema,
they often use this screen.
And currently we're using this widescreen, or no, currently I think we're using
this HD TV screen 16.9.
So that is the, so in these numbers are saying what kind of ratio it is.
So this is 16.
Oh, this is 16 and this is nine high.
Um, yeah.
Think about what kind of aspect ratio are using.
Maybe it's for a book or maybe it's for television.
So when I'm going to plan a scene, um, sometimes before I'm going to draw the
whole, the whole scene and so on,
I'm starting to draw this plane, this ground plane.
And you don't have to draw it in this perspective.
You can also draw it like this map.
And later I will show more.
But then you can think,
I want to have this character
that's saying hi to this character.
And I think I want to have the camera here.
And maybe there's a tree here
and maybe that's a tree here.
So when you do this,
this can help when you're later,
there's something helping
because there's here this dino,
beautiful dino.
So like this,
is attacking these two characters.
And we want to move the camera to here.
And then we still know here's a tree
and here's a tree and this tree is falling on.
And then you can use that to create a shot.
So for example,
Here we're just seeing two characters
and here we're seeing this dino and these two characters.
Like this, best drawing ever.
But a lot of times I'm making doodles like this
to figure out what I want to draw
and if it will work and et cetera.
Not every drawing needs to be perfect,
especially not with storyboarding.
So also try to learn all these different shots.
So here this camera, when we see the full body,
it's called a full shot.
So that means the camera is a little bit further
from the object we're viewing it.
So a medium shot is when we can see the character from a little bit above the
knees.
Here we're calling this a medium shot. Then the camera moves in a bit closer.
So a close shot is like this here and then we're seeing this part of the
character.
An extreme close shot is when the camera is really in his face.
So these kinds of shots are often used and I think this close shot and a medium
shot is most used.
So a full shot can really help to tell you what's going on.
An extreme close shot can help you to show the emotion really clear.
But we're not using it that much.
A really great way to practice this is to go watch an
a movie and try to try to see if you can recognize all those different shots.
So but there are there are more for example the establishing shots and
establishing shots
I think you can really recognize it if you're watching a movie and most of the
time the
the opening shot of the the movie is for example we're seeing and the movie
starts
and we're seeing New York so all these buildings with the sun and then we're
going to the
to one flat building like this here and then we're going to the maybe we're
seeing one
window in this flat building with this character like this here.
So these are all establishing shots and it helps you as the viewer understand
where we are in this
world and then you go closer because it gives you this sense that you you know
where everything is
and so on. So when our two persons are talking in a shot oftentimes it's called
the two shots
and later I will tell a bit more about that but you also have three shots or
four shots
or five shots. A three shot is when there are three characters in a shot, four
is when four and etc.
You also have these camera shots like an over the shoulder.
So we're looking over the shoulder to the other person.
There's this bird view that's often used in establishing shots and it's called
bird view
because we
it's like we have this bird here.
And this bird is looking at this person.
We also have a frog view.
For example, if a frog is here
and we have this person here,
this frog looks up
and then the shot will look a bit like this.
So when this person,
so this is looking like this,
it's looking really big.
So we're feeling really tiny and small.
So you have this bird view.
Point of view, for example,
if you are looking through glasses
or you're looking through the bushes or something,
or when you're looking through a car trunk,
that's called a POV, point of view.
So some shows or movies are using that a lot
in creative ways.
The Dutch angle.
And I'm Dutch, but I don't know why it's called Dutch.
I think it's even originally from Germany, but, uh, that's meant when.
The, the horizon line is, uh, at an angle.
So, and that can help give you this weird, strange feeling.
And it's, it's put you literally off balance this, uh, a lot of times used
in action scenes or horror scenes, or when a person gets sick or something.
Um, um, that's used with the Dutch angle.
So, um, here I'm showing a bit more about it, uh, bird and frog perspective.
So we have the camera, the eye line and the object like this person.
So this eye line is the line that comes out of the.
the camera. When we are looking and we're looking in front of us we have this
eye line.
So this horizon line is at the same line as our eye line. I'm talking a bit more
about
this in the perspective facebook. The base thing is that this eye line
determines the perspective
of the character. For example if we have the camera and this camera is looking
up this eye
line goes up like this and it means that here it was we were at the same height
but here we're
smaller so we're looking up at this person. Now and this is this frog
perspective it's like there's
a frog here looking upwards and here this is the birth view but this you can
also call this
frog view the low angle or this birth view and high angle and this can be used
to create for example
here we're a frog so we're weak but here we're bigger so maybe here we're a
super big monster
like in here so now the camera is really strong and this person is
this person is weak and we are strong and in this case this character is strong
and we're weak
so camera angles and more
so this doesn't tell us anything and there are movie directors who are using a
lot of these shots
and that gives them this own style
But they are basically breaking the rules, but then you really need to know what
you
are doing and it's really difficult to do that good.
So if we want to have this cat and mouse scene making it look really dangerous,
we make this
cat big and this mouse small.
So if we're looking here, so here, if this was the movie set here, we have the
camera
was looking down because here's this cat and here's this mouse.
So the cat is close to the camera and you can try this out with your phone or
your own
camera.
So the cat is close to the camera.
So the cat appears bigger than it is.
And the mouse is farther away from the camera and then that makes this mouse
smaller.
For example, we can also turn it around.
Here we have this cat.
Mouse, and we put the camera here.
Then we have, so if we would draw that here, then we have this mouse
isn't really big and it's cat.
It's small.
So this could also actually work.
So try to, um, but then, yeah, it's different.
You can see that's because the mouse is closer to the camera, et cetera.
Um, yeah, here I'm telling this about this, uh, low angle.
So here we have this character.
So basically this is a bit like, uh, the camera is looking a bit.
Nope, not much.
And here we have this.
person, but this person is way bigger and stands here. So you get this, this
kind of shot.
And we're using this low, here, this camera is really low. And it makes this
monster really
big. It really goes over the person. So weak, strong, try to think in those
terms.
So here I'm using this Dutch angle and it makes it really dynamic and actionful
by
using this angle in this shot. So lenses, here you can see all the different
lenses.
So we're drawing, but still we can think about what kind of lenses do we want to
use?
So camera has a lens and maybe you have that on your, on your phone.
So a wide angle lens and that means for example if we're looking at this camera
and a wide angle lens means basically we get this really wide view, so like
this.
So when we're looking at this house here and a lot of times it means that the
camera is close to the object.
This object looks really big, but you also get this distorted look because of
the perspective.
Here you can see here you get this, even this three point perspective.
You can see this really strong perspective, right?
And that's because of this, that the camera is close and it's a wide angle shot.
So our eyes is a bit...
So this is the size of the lens, so 40 to 60 millimeter.
And you can compare that to our eyes.
So that means we are at medium range and we're looking at this house.
Maybe it's a bit further away.
So something like this.
But you can see this is wider than this is.
So telescope lens, and maybe you've watched through a telescope or bionicles
is when the camera is really far away.
And here's the house.
But the lens is very small or narrow and you get this.
So that makes, there's almost no perspective.
And it's really weird.
Try to, maybe you have that.
Maybe you have your bionicles,
or telescope, or maybe once you're in the city, or when you're at a tourist
location,
you often have these kind of telescopes. And when you're watching through it,
you almost see no perspective. And also, here, this grass in the foreground is
really out of
focus. But that's a bit of a different thing. But you can really use this for
different
goals. For example, here, I'm showing that in a lot of skate videos. I grew up
in the 90s,
and we always had, everywhere you saw these music clips, or skateboarders, and
they used this
really extreme close-up, and you really get this distorted view, where this part
looks really big,
and this small, and so on. So here, the 40, 60 millimeter, this is the camera
you want to use
most, because that feels, this feels normal, because this lens is like our eyes.
So in a
movie, if you want to see, let something look plain and normal, you use this. If
you want to make
something look special, you use this, or you use this. And this effect, and here
you can see it,
there's no perspective. Yeah, this, so this lens is used for when we're looking
from someone from a
great distance. Camera movement. So when we're in, when we're making
storyboards,
we need to use different camera movements.
Actually here, it's not really a camera movement,
it's a zoom in.
So the camera stays at the same position,
but the lens is going different,
and we're zooming in because of that.
So this is called the zoom in.
And in storyboarding, you're using these kind of arrows
to show that.
We also have a pan, and that means when the camera,
so we're starting here with the camera,
and then we're going move to the side to here.
So for example, it's like this.
So here, and then we're panning to the right to this shot.
And this is called a pan.
We also have a tilt.
And for example, we're starting here,
and we're going up.
and you can use these kind of arrows.
You can also draw them like this.
I think it's better to even draw them like this,
because here the shot moves up to this.
But that's called the tilt.
Oh yeah, one thing for the zoom in,
in when you're making a real movie,
you can also, besides the zoom in,
you can also put the camera,
move the camera closer to the person.
And this is called, I think out of my head, trunking.
So here we're moving the camera closer to the person we're filming.
Camera movements with pens.
Here we, this is the pen I just showed,
for horizontal pen.
And you can use this for this action scene.
So sometimes in storyboarding,
you can use these arrows to show the car is moving.
Vertical pen.
So yeah, just what I've shown earlier.
Or you can also use a diagonal pen.
So that means when we have this and for example,
this can be really useful when we're going from down from a hill.
And we follow this person so that would move here.
So like this here.
And this arrow means basically that we follow this person like this.
So here are some more.
So this is like the zooming.
You can call it the truck in or a truck out, zoom out.
Clockwise rotation truck in.
So this is basically the same as this one.
But then the camera rotates.
Maybe I can.
So what basically is happening.
We're going, zooming in, but also the camera rotates, right?
So here you can see I'm rotating the camera.
So that's what's happening there.
Here, it's a little bit different.
Here, we're starting here.
So we're starting here and then we zoom out or check out.
And we're going back to this.
So this is a counter-clockwise rotation check out.
And this means, this is to clarify
which way it rotates to.
But here you can see the movements of the camera,
of the panel by these arrows.
You can also use this tracking a bit.
For example, here we're seeing all these people
and they are saying, what is that?
Is it a plane?
Is it an UFO?
No, it's Superman.
And then they're zooming in with this, with this truck, truck in.
So this is a little bit different, but that's also interesting.
For, for example, when there's an earthquake, everything shakes.
And you can use these symbols on your panels to clarify that, that shaking.
So blur, and I talked a bit, a little bit about that with the different lenses.
Um, so, and it can really help with creating depth.
For example, here we have this palm tree and it feels close to us or, um, it, it
gives this
effect of, uh, framing, but here we have this character that's really, um, on
focus.
And because of that, uh, our, I really focus on that person, the same here.
The background is out of focus and this person's in focus.
So that helps us read what we're trying to tell.
A rack focus.
So this means basically we're starting with what's basically happening.
I can draw it out here.
Oh, yeah, I already drew it.
So this shot starts with, he is in focus and then the next shot, this is in
focus.
And there's this kind of transition between those, um, those shots.
Uh, animated backgrounds.
So I talked a bit about this with the, uh, the pen shots, but here I use these
arrows
to show that's the background.
is moving behind this, uh, this character.
So there's this moving backgrounds, but the, the person stays on the same place.
So that's different with the pen, but with these arrows, I'm trying to, to show
that,
uh, moving backgrounds. You can also use it. For example, when you're riding in
this, uh, on this,
on this road, the car stays on the same position, but the background, uh,
changes.
Maybe, uh, the road goes that way. Um, so for example, that means that you have
maybe a road
like this, but then the here, if this is the car, then here is the camera.
The camera follows the car. And that means the background is moving and the car
is not,
um, you can also use this.
I think, oh, is this also a parallax? Parallaxing?
Um, I don't know the term, but that's used in, uh, in gaming and in 2D games,
where we have all these different objects, uh, oh, parallax effect.
So that these objects, so this tree is in the foreground and these mountains in
the background.
So these mountains are farther away and they, this is basically a pen.
So we're following this character and walking on this path.
But if we're doing that, you can move the tree to the left quite fast.
But these mountains also move a bit and it has to do with the perspective.
So for example, here, the camera is moving.
And here we have the tree and we're following this person walking, right?
So the camera moves along with the person that is walking to this side.
Then we also have here all these mountains but those are really,
really far away. So these are here are all these mountains and here's all the
tree and
but here remember those lenses are like this. So these mountains are really far
away so that
means that they are moving slower and that the things in the foreground move
faster.
Maybe it's a bit hard to tell but try to, especially in 2D animations,
once you see a shot like this, try to see the different layers of the
backgrounds and how fast they are moving.
So
When we're going to make storyboards, there are some camera rules we need to
use.
For example, the 180 camera rule. So when we're filming,
for example, we have two characters talking to each other.
Um, so maybe one shot filming here and then another shot for filming here and
then here,
then it's really hard to follow who is who. There's this trick for, and that's
the 180 rule.
So that means that if we have two persons, we draw this imaginary line between
those persons
and we're putting the cameras only on this side of the
of this border. So this helps
see where we're looking at. Because if you're going over this border then it
makes it harder
to follow what are we looking at. So for example here I'm using these shots.
So this is camera one. So here we're seeing this person is left and this person
is right.
In shot two this person is also on the left and this person is on the right. In
three this person
is also on the left and on the right. So that makes it really simple to follow.
But if we're
to watch it from this view then the person with the hat is on the left and then
this
person is on the right and that makes it confusing so normally you don't use
that
camera on the other side you can maybe if you're watching an
tiffy where they're interviewing people on the table they're also often using
this
and you can cross the border but then you need to show clearly for example it's
an establishing shot
what is happening or when you're using an orbit camera so in this case we have
this camera here
looking at here but then it moves all the way around and so there's this famous
2000 action
movie that's also using this but then this called 360 orbit camera when the
camera is moving around
that's the character
so rotating with the camera around the subject
it's used for action shots it's not often used but it's this cool effect I
wanted to share
so rotation of the camera so this is a bit like a pen but if we're just moving
it like
straight plane like this it's kind of boring so it's more interesting if we're
using this
perspective like this and then we're seeing that so if this person was a box
first we're seeing this perspective the f from front and then we're seeing the
back of the person
like this and then we're even seeing more of the back
of the person so like this so that makes it a bit more easy easier to understand
so this
also a pen but then the camera is rotating and it helps me giving this
interesting shots
um a really good way to get better at storyboarding is to
analyze movies so go watch a movie and try to recognize the shots on now we're
seeing
establishing shots and now it's a long shot and now we're looking at medium
shots and a close-up
an extreme close-up an extreme closure close-up so they're really building up so
it's really like
and here here's the action in the character and we're starting with establishing
shots the medium
shots
and then the close shot so we're building up this tension and it's also easy to
feel for the
character so oh we are in the desert and i see two oh no no the establishing
shots we're starting the
movie we're seeing a desert oh in the desert are two characters standing in
front of each other
oh they have a gun and they're looking mean oh i can see the tension in the eyes
i can see the gun
and you see his reaction oh he's going to draw the gun so that you're telling a
story with these
kinds of shots and again a great way to learn this is to go watch a movie take
your sketchbook
and make quick scribbles of what you can see maybe you can freeze the movie to
to analyze the shot better
This is really a great way of learning storyboarding.
Go watch a movie and sketch these shots
and try to think of what does director wants to tell
with this kind of shots.